Mss.B.P212
American Philosophical Society
Sir James Paget correspondence, 1784-1932
Mss.B.P212
American Philosophical Society
0.75 Linear feet 196 items
196 items.
These letters were assembled by Lady Paget as a collection of autographs. Most are addressed to Paget, and their subjects include medicine, science, and family.
Paget, James, Sir, 1814-1899
Box 1-2
Scope and Contents Note
The collection is comprised of the correspondence of British surgeon and pathologist Sir James Paget, but also includes letters that were assembled by Lady Paget and their daughter Kate as a collection of autographs. Many of the letters are addressed to Sir James, and their subjects include medicine, science, and family matters. Many of the correspondents in this collection of more than 192 items are from Paget’s fellow members of the Royal College of Surgeons. However, many letters come from acquaintances in a wide variety of scientific disciplines. Some letters to Lady Paget and her daughter specifically mention donations to their autograph collection. For example, a November 28, 1835 letter from James’ brother George to Lady Paget describes an enclosed autograph from “the celebrated John Dalton, the discoverer of the laws of Chemical combination,” while another note from Sir George Burrows to Kate on December 5, 1864 simply mentions an “enclosed autograph [that] will add to the value of your collection.”
Of the letters to and from Sir James Paget covering a period of more than sixty years, no single correspondent stands out for either frequency or length of correspondence. Instead, this collection represents the wide variety of scientific interests among his correspondents. For example, an August 7, 1864 letter from the amateur chemist and physician John Davy, the brother of the famous chemist Sir Humphrey Davy, thanks Sir James for “the gracious manner in which you received my paper on the freezing of the egg.” More than a year later on September 22, 1865 the engineer Sir Henry Bessemer wrote to him to request the return of a manuscript. Twenty years later on June 29, 1885 noted British social reformer Edwin Chadwick wrote to Paget complaining about “the state of the air” in government buildings, which allegedly caused an acquaintance A. Siddell of the Colonial Office to suffer from carbunckles.
However, predictably much of the Paget correspondence deals with medical, professional or routine matters. One of Paget’s correspondents is his colleague in the Royal College of Surgeons Sir James Clark, who wrote to Paget on January 30, 1861, regarding the need to replace the late Dr. Baily, formerly Lecturer on Midwifery, who had committed suicide by consuming prussic acid. Eleven months later on December 28, 1861 Paget’s colleague Sir Benjamin Collins Brodie, the physiologist and surgeon who pioneered research on bone and joint diseases, wrote to ask Paget to recommend a candidate for a position. A most interesting letter from his colleague, the neurosurgeon Victor Horsley, dated May 4, 1886 reports that he had just returned from Lyon, where he had witnessed rabies inoculations conducted by French microbiologist Louis Pasteur, who developed a vaccine from the spinal cord of an infected rabbit.
Sir James and Lady Pagets' other prominent correspondents include the botanist Joseph Dalton Hooker and anatomist/zoologist Richard Owen. However, the contents of these letters is unrelated to medicine. In a January 10, 1884 Owen refers simply to the “small work” remaining to be done in order to furnish his new natural history museum, while in a second letter from June 15 he confesses that “My physiological studies are now limited to progressive failures of vital force in my own frame.”
Early American History Note
This manuscript collection falls outside the geographic scope of the Early American guide (British North America and the United States before 1840). It may be of interest to scholars interested in global history, international relations, imperialism, or the U.S. in the world.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Purchased from Dawson ($550.00) and accessioned, 1959 (1959 1261ms).
Biographical/Historical note
Sir James Paget, a surgeon, was elected to the American Philosophical Society in 1854.
Abel, Frederick Augustus, Sir, 1826-1902; Adams, John Couch, 1819-1892; Agassiz, Louis, 1807-1873; Airy, George Biddell, Sir, 1801-1892; Babbage, Charles, 1791-1871; Billings, John S., (John Shaw), 1838-1913; Blackwell, Elizabeth, 1821-1910; Clark, Andrew, 1856-1922; Cuvier, Georges, Baron, 1769-1832; Darwin, Charles, 1809-1882; Davy, Humphry,Sir,1778-1829.; Dewar, James, d. 1788; Edison, Thomas A., (Thomas Alva), 1847-1931; Ellerton, John Lodge, 1801-1873; Ericsson, John, 1803-1889; Faraday, Michael, 1791-1867; Flower, William Henry, 1831-1899; Forbes, Edward, 1815-1854; Galton, Douglas Strutt, 1822-1899; Galton, Francis, Sir, 1822-1911; Geikie, Archibald, Sir, 1835-1924; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888; Hooker, Joseph Dalton, Sir, 1817-1911; Hooker, William Jackson, Sir, 1785-1865; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859; Huxley, Thomas Henry, 1825-1895; Lister, Joseph, Baron, 1827-1912; Lubbock, J. W., (John William), 1803-1865; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875; Murchison, Roderick Impey, Sir, 1792-1871; Osler, William, Sir, 1849-1919; Prestwick, Joseph, Sir; Rolleston, George, 1829-1881; Siemens, Charles William, Sir, 1823-1883; Simpson, James Young, Sir, 1811-1870; Spencer, Herbert, 1820-1903; Stephenson, Robert, 1803-1859; Tyndall, John, 1820-1893; Virchow, Rudolf Ludwig Karl, 1821-1902; Wallace, Albert Russel; Watson, Thomas, -- Sir.; Wheatstone, Charles, Sir, 1802-1875; Autographs.; Beyond Early America; Medicine.; Science.
- Papers
  - Table of Contents, BP212
  - Collection of letters from various persons, 1784-1932; Paget, James, Sir, 1814-1899 (Box 1)
    Separated Materials note
    Collection items are (with a few exceptions) individually foldered.
    Scope and Contents note
    D. 192 pieces and 1 photograph. Various sizes. Chiefly medical men's letters and scientists. Table of contents available.
  - Letter to James McGrigor, Glasgow, Oct. 30, 1784; 10x8; Watt, James, 1736-1819 (Box 1)
    Birmingham, A.L.S. 4p.,add.,end. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Concerning Arkwright. Steam engines. Canals.
  - Letter to [Charles] Burney, Chelsea, Nov. 21, 1794; 9x7-1/4; Royal Society (Great Britain). (Box 1)
    Printed L.filled in in ms.S.: Jos.Banks. 1p.and add. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Notifies him of his election.
  - Au Citoyen Gaugé, May 31, 1796; 9x7; Seine (France). Bureau du Domaine National (Box 1)
    Architecte. Rue Hiacinthe Michel. La Loi du 28 ventòse dernier.. .; Prairial onze, an 4 Printed D.filled in in ms.S.: Guillotin. 4p. In French. (see Sir James Paget. Collection.. .)
  - Letter to [John] Bostock, Liverpool, Aug. 26, [1805]; 9-1/2x7-1/2; Davy, Humphry, Sir, 1778-1829 (Box 1)
    A.L.S. 2p.and add.,end. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Asks a favor. Is delighted over his successful career.
  - Letter to [William] Scoresby, Junior, Whitby, December, 1815; 9x7-1/2; Jameson, Robert, 1774-1854 (Box 1)
    A.L.S. 2p. and add., end. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Recommends a young man for a post and asks that he write to Dr. Home about the man.
  - Letter to [John] Bostock, Liverpool, Aug. 13, 1815; 10x8; Brewster, David, Sir, 1781-1868 (Box 1)
    A.L.S. 3p.and add.,end. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Concerning their publications. Galvanism.
  - Letter to Paget, April 10, 1818; Rennie, John
  - Letter to Mr. Paget, April 14, 1818; Rennie, Mrs. [John]
  - Broadside addressed to Sam[ue]l Paget, Esq., Bidder, George Parker, 1806-1878
  - By permission of the right worshipful the Mayor...Master Bidder, the celebrated Menta Calculator.., Aug.7, 1819; 9-1/2x7-1/2; Bidder, George Parker, 1806-1878 (Box 1)
    Broadside S.: George Bidder. 1p., add.: Sam[ue]l Paget. Printed for J. Shalders, Queen-Street, [Yarmouth]. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...)
  - Letter to Charles Wing, June 14, 1822; 9x7-1/4; Abernethy, John, 1764-1831 (Box 1)
    A.L.S. 1p.and add. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Concerning a monster child.
  - Pass to Mrs. Henry T. Moor to the surgical lectures, Oct., 1825; 3x4-1/2; Abernethy, John, 1764-1831 (Box 1)
    A.D.S. 1p. (see Sir James Paget. Collection... )
  - Letter to Mrs. W[illia]m Rathbone, Liverpool, June 4, 1832; 9x7; Spurzheim, J. G., (Johann Gaspar), 1776-1832 (Box 1)
    Paris, A.L.S. 3p.and add.,end. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) His reasons for going to America. Phrenology.
  - Letter to Henry Paget, Yarmouth, Feb. 10, 1833; 10x8; Hooker, William Jackson, Sir, 1785-1865 (Box 1)
    Glascow, A.L.S. 4p.,add. "by favor of Dawson Turner" (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Would like to exchange plants.
  - Receipt to Mr. Johnston, Sept. 27, 1833; 3x7-1/4; Dalton, John, 1766-1844
    A.D.S.with initials. 1p. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...)
  - Letter to James Paget, Yarmouth, Nov. 30, 1833; 8x5; Hooker, Joseph Dalton, Sir, 1817-1911
    Glasgow, A.L.S. 1p.and add. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Thanks for plants.
  - Letter to [Arthur C. Paget?], Ealing, Nov. 15, [1834?]; 9x7-1/4; Watson, Thomas, Sir, 1792-1882
    A.L.S. 2p.and add. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Prescribes for complaint.
  - Letter to Mrs. Paget, Nov. 28, 1835; 6-1/2x7-1/2; Paget, George Edward, 1809-1892
    Cambridge, A.L.S. 1p. Post-script to a letter, on address sheet. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Sends autograph for collection.
  - To the Governors of the Finsbury Dispensary, March 15, 1841; 8x5; Birkett, John, 1815-1904
    Broadside. 1p. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...)
  - Letter to [Sir] James Paget, London, Nov. 5, 1841; 10-1/2x8-1/4; Vrolik, W. (Willem), 1801-1863
    Amsterdam, A.L.S. 3p.and add. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Concerning publications. Forwards publications, one of which is for Richard Owen.
  - Letter to [Sir] J[ames] Paget, Feb. 10, 1842; 4-1/2x3-3/4; Stanley, Edward, 1791-1862
    A.L.S. 2p.and add. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Asks him to help him with a cataloging job.
  - Letter to John Abinday(?), April 21, 1842; 7x4-1/2; Faraday, Michael, 1791-1867
    A.L.S. 1p.(see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Introduces his brother-in-law and asks him to examine his sketches.
  - Letter to [Sir] James Paget, Feb. 7, Feb. 8, 1845; 7x4-1/2; Wilson, Erasmus, Sir, 1809-1884
    A.L.S. 3p. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Concerning the structure of muscle.
  - Letter to the President and Vice Presidents of the Royal College of Surgeons, Jan. 23, 1847; 9-1/4x7-1/4; Home, Everard, Sir, 1756-1832
    A.L. in 3rd.P. 1p. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Aceepts invitation.
  - Letter to [Sir James Paget], May 5, 1849; 7x4-1/2; Forbes, Edward, 1815-1854
    A.L.S. 4p. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Botany.
  - Letter to [Sir James Paget], Aug. 23, 1849; 7x4-1/2; Brodie, Benjamin C. (Benjamin Collins), Sir, 1783-1862
    A.L.S. 2p.,end. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Has ordered the work he wants.
  - Letter to [Sir] J[ohn] E. Gray, July 6, 1850; 5-1/2x3-1/2; Spence. Kirby (Kirby, William, 1759-1850)
    A.L.S. 2p.,end. (see Sir James Paget Collection...) Notifies him of the death of W.Kirby.
  - Letter to [Sir James] Paget, Oct. 8, 1850; 8x5; Blackwell, Elizabeth, 1821-1910
    A.L.S. 1p.and end.with extract from Lady Paget's letter concerning E.Blackwell (see Sir James Paget. Collection) Must visit relatives, but will return to course.
  - Letter to ----, June 18, 1851; 7x4-1/2; Adams, John Couch, 1819-1892
    A.L.S. 2p. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Refuses invitation. Thanks for pass to the theater.
  - List of members of the Philosophical Club, December 20, 1855; Photocopies.; Royal Society of London
  - Letter to Thomas Dobson, April 8, 1856; 8-1/2x5-1/2; Quetelet, Adolphe, 1796-1874
    Brussels, A.L.S. 2p. In French. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Concerning meteorological observations from the Royal Society.
  - Letter to Mr. Holymann, May 19, 1857; 8-3/4x5-1/2; Bunsen, R. (Robert), 1811-1899
    A.L.S. 2p. In German. (see Sir James Paget.Collection...)
  - Letter to [Sir] Edw[ard] Sabine, Sept. 28, 1857; 5x5-1/2; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    Berlin, A.L.S. 1p. In French. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Concerning page proofs of a publication.
  - Letter to [Sir James] Paget, Jan. 26, 1859; 7x4-1/2; Locock, Charles, Sir, 1799-1875
    A.L.S. 1p. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Cannot dine with him, for his son is leaving for 5 years, and he wishes to be with him.
  - Letter to [Sir James] Paget, Jan. 30, 1861; 7x4-1/2; Clark, James, Sir, 1788-1870
    Surrey, A.L.S. 3p. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Concerning the death of Baly.
  - Letter to Col. [Sir John Henry] Lefroy, Feb. 5, 1861; 13x8; Whitworth, Joseph, 1803-1887
    Woolwich, A.L.S. 1p.,end. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Concerning testing a gun.
  - Letter to [Sir James Paget], Dec. 28, 1861; 7x4-1/2; Brodie, Benjamin C. (Benjamin Collins), Sir, 1783-1862
    A.L.S. 2p. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Asks for recommendation of a man.
  - Letter to [Sir James] Paget, [1861]; 7x4-3/4; Clark, James, Sir, 1788-1870
    Tuesday, A.L.S. 4p. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Concerning the death of Baly and need to replace him with Paget.
  - Letter to Mrs. [Lady Lydia North] Paget, April 29, 1862; 7x4-1/2; Hooker, William Jackson, Sir, 1785-1865
    A.L.S. 1p. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Will send flowers as she wishes.
  - Letter to Mrs. [Lady Lydian North] Paget, Nov. 28, 1862; 7x4-1/2; Owen, Richard, 1804-1892
    A.L.S. 2p. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Accepts invitation.
  - Letter to ----, Nov. 12, 1863; 7x4-1/2; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    A.L.S. 1p. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Asks him to call and see some bones and horns.
  - Signatures of members present and amounts paid, Dec. 10, 1863; 12-3/4x7-3/4; Nobody's Friends (Club)
    D. 2p.and end. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Sir James Paget is among the signers.
  - Letter to Dr. M. Holymann, Dec. 22, 1863; 7x4-1/2; Faraday, Michael, 1791-1867
    A.L.S. 2p. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Is delighted with the recognition given science.
  - Letter to Mr. Holymann, Dec. 23, 1863; 7x4-1/2; Tyndall, John, 1820-1893
    A.L.S. 4p. (see Sir James Paget. Collection.. .) Describes the two lectures on electricity and sound which he will give to the princesses.
  - Signatures of members present and amounts paid, Feb. 2, 1864; 12-3/4x7-3/4; Nobody's Friends (Club)
    D. 1p.and end. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Sir James Paget is among the signers.
  - Letter to [Sir James] Paget, May 17, 1864; 8x5; Armstrong, W. G. (William George), Baron, 1810-1900
    Newcastle-on-Tyne, A.L.S. 1p. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Has not received publication yet.
  - Letter to [Sir William] Bowman, July 11, 1864; 7x4-1/2; Wheatstone, Charles, Sir, 1802-1875
    A.L.S. 1p. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Encloses list for election for the Horticultural society.
  - Letter to [Sir] James Paget, Aug. 7, 1864; 7x4-1/2; Davy, John, 1790-1868
    A.L.S. 4p. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Thanks him for the way he received a paper. Praises him for his medical work.
  - Letter to Kate Paget, Dec. 5, 1864; 5-1/2x3-1/2; Burrows, George, Sir, 1801-1887
    A.L.S. 1p. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Gives her his autograph for her collection.
  - Letter to [Sir William Jackson?] Hooker, Feb. 24, 1865; 7x4-1/2; Murchison, Roderick Impey, Sir, 1792-1871
    A.L.S. 2p. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Asks him to come to the meetings of the Royal geographical society of London.
  - Letter to [Sir James Paget], June 2, 1865; 6-1/4x4; Fairbairn, William, Sir, 1789-1874
    Westminster, A.L.S. 1p. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Thanks for advice about a dentist.
  - Letter to [Sir James Paget], June 3, 1865; 7x4-1/2; Stokes, Henry Sewell, 1808-1895
    Dublin, A.L.S. 1p. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Introduces his son.
  - Letter to [Sir James Paget], Sept. 22, 1865; 8x5; Bessemer, Henry, Sir, 1813-1898
    London, A.L.S. 1p. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Asks for copy of an article he wrote.
  - Letter to [Sir James] Paget, April 17, 1866; 8-1/2x5-1/2; Langenbeck, Maximilian Adolf, 1818-1887
    Berlin, A.L.S. 1p. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Introduces a young doctor.
  - Letter to [Sir James] Paget, June 21, 1866; 7x4-1/4; Fergusson, William, Sir, 1808-1877
    A.L.S. 2p. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Asks that he join him in visiting a patient.
  - Letter to ----, July 3, 1866; 10x8; Ericsson, John, 1803-1889
    New York, A.L.S. 1p. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Sorry the letter of introduction arrived too late to do anything. Pays £20.
  - Letter to [Sir William Robert] Grove, July 18, 1866; 7-1/4x4-1/2; Ramsay, A. C., (Andrew Crombie), 1814-1891
    A.L.S. 1p. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Will answer his note tomorrow.
  - Letter to F. A. Paget, Sept. 28, 1866; 7x4-1/2; Coles, Cowper Phipps, 1819-1870
    A.L.S. 3p. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Hopes he will win the expensive test.
  - Letter to [Sir James] Paget, Feb. 13, 1867; 7x4-1/2; Parkes, Edmund A. (Edmund Alexander), 1819-1876
    A.L.S. 2p. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Invites him to dine with him and Hooker.
  - Letter to Katie [Paget], Feb. 14, 1867; 7x4-1/2; Owen, Richard, 1804-1892
    A.L.S. 4p. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Concerning memories of a dinner. Concerning the honors her father has received
  - Letter to [Sir] James Paget, Feb. 28, 1867; 7-1/4x4-1/2; Lubbock, John, Sir, 1834-1913
    A.L.S. 2p. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Thanks for his favors and hopes he will visit again.
  - Letter to W.E.(?) Paget, March 14, 1867; 6x3-3/4; Babbage, Charles, 1791-1871
    A.L.S. 3p. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Concerning engines.
  - Letter to Sir James Paget, June 27, 1867; 7x4-1/2; Galton, Douglas Strutt, 1822-1899
    A.L.S. 2p. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Appreciated his letter of congratulations.
  - Letter to [Sir] J[ames] Paget, July 15, 1867; 7x4-1/2; Nasmyth, James, 1808-1890
    Kent, A.L.S. 1p. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Denies having written the pamphlet in question.
  - Letter to J. A. Paget, Jan. 2, 1868; 8x5; Siemens, Charles William, Sir, 1823-1883
    Westmister, A.L.S. 1p. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Will see him Friday.
  - Letter to Miss Paget, Aug. 11, 1868; 7x4-1/2; Rolleston, George, 1829-1881
    Oxford, A.L.S. 2p. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Sends photograph. Friendly letter.
  - Letter to [Sir James] Paget, Sept. 26, 1868; 7x4-1/2; Jenner, William, Sir, 1815-1898
    A.L.S. 2p. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Concerning visitors for this evening.
  - Letter to [Sir] Francis Galton, Dec. 15, 1868; 7-1/4x4-1/2; Wallace, Alfred Russel, 1823-1913
    A.L.S. 2p. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Accepts post in the royal geographical society of London. Refuses dinner invitation.
  - Letter to Mrs. Paget, Dec. 24, 1868; 8x5; Babbage, Charles, 1792-1871
    A.L.S. 1p. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Accepts invitation.
  - Letter to Mrs. [Lady Lydia North] Paget, July (?) 7, 1869; 7-1/4x4-1/2; Huxley, Thomas Henry, 1825-1895
    A.L.S. 3p. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Sorry not to have seen her yesterday.
  - Letter to [Sir James] Paget, March 22, 1869; 7x4-1/2; Gull, William Withey, Sir, 1816-1890
    A.L.S. 1p. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Will come by the house.
  - Letter to ----, May 29, 1869; 8-1/4x5-1/4; Velatoy(?)
    L. 1p. In French. Incomplete. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Concerning a tumor (cancer?).
  - Letter to "My dear Sister", Sept. 9, 1869; 7x4-1/2; Wheatstone, Charles, Sir, 1802-1875
    A.L.S. 2p. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Makes arrangements for a visit.
  - Letter to [Sir James Paget], 1870; 6x4; Holland, Henry, Sir, 1788-1873
    Sunday, [ca.]. A.L.S. 1p. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Medical opinions.
  - Letter to Miss Paget, Jan. 31, 1870; 7-1/4x4-1/2; Huxley, Thomas Henry, 1825-1895
    A.L.S. 3p. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Recommends where she send a poem. Concerning translating work.
  - Letter to Mrs. [Lady Lydia North] Paget, March 9, 1870; 7x4-1/2; Blackwell, Elizabeth, 1821-1910
    [?]. A.L.S. 1p. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Has printed a discourse and will furnish copies if it could be read at "Mother's Meetings etc."
  - Letter to Mrs. Paget, June 2, 1870; 6-1/2x4-1/2; Babbage, Charles, 1791-1871
    A.L.S. 2p. Mutilated. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Thanks for her suggestions. Concerning an engine.
  - Letter to Miss Paget, 1870?; 7x4-1/2; Rolleston, George, 1829-1881
    [ca.]. A.L.S. 4p. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Describes his vacation.
  - Letter to Misses Paget, April 3, 1871; 4-1/2x3-1/2; Hooker, Joseph Dalton, Sir, 1817-1911
    A.L.S. 4p. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Friendly letter. Describes the route he will take on his tour of Africa.
  - Letter to Mrs. [Lady Lydia North] Paget, May 29, 1871; 7x4-1/2; Spencer, Herbert, 1820-1903
    London, A.L.S. 1p. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Refuses invitation.
  - Letter to Sir James Paget., Bart., Dec. 2, 1871; 7-1/2x4-1/2; Airy, George Biddell, Sir, 1801-1892
    London, A.L.S. 2p. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Asks him to become a vice-president of the Royal society.
  - Letter to Sir James Paget, bart., Dec. 6, 1871; 7x4-1/2; Sabine, Edward, Sir, 1788-1883
    A.L.S. 1p. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Thanks for his note of congratulations.
  - Letter to Holymann, Dec. 16, 1871; 7-1/4x4-1/2; Abel, Frederick Augustus, Sir, 1826-1902
    A.L.S. 2p.(see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Is delighted the prince is progressing.
  - Letter to [Sir James] Paget, July 27, 1873; 7x4-1/2; Watson, Thomas, Sir, 1792-1882
    A.L.S. 2p. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Has just returned from the funeral of E.L.Ormerod and agrees to write a memorial
  - Letter to Sir James [Paget], Sept. 27, 1873; 7x4-1/2; Galton, Francis, Sir, 1822-1911
    London, A.L.S. 2p. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Thanks for his letter on scientific men.
  - Letter to [C.E. Brown-Se'quard], Oct. 26, 1873; 8x5; Agassiz, Louis, 1807-1873
    Cambridge, Mass., A.L.S. 1p In French. (see Sir James Paget. Collection... ) Concerning experiments and work at Harvard, with possibility of a permanent position.
  - Letter to Miss Paget, June 9, 1877; 7x4-1/2; Hewett, Prescott Gardner, 1812-1891
    A.L.S. 2p.(see Sir James Paget.Collection...) Sends her a souvenir.
  - Letter to Katie [Paget], June 26, 1877; 7-1/4x4-1/2; Acland, Henry W. (Henry Wentworth), 1815-1900
    Oxford, A.L.S. 4p. (see Sir James Paget. Collection.. .) Is sorry the present is not ready.
  - Letter to [George John] Romanes, Dec. 9, 1880; 7x4-1/4; Huggins, William, 1820-1884
    A.L.S. 2p. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Gives directions how to reach his house.
  - Letter to [Sir James] Paget, March 12, 1881; 7x4-1/4; Watson, Thomas, Sir, 1792-1882
    A.L.S. 2p. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Thanks for publication.
  - Letter to Geo[rge] J[ohn] Romanes, March 17, 1881; 8x5; Dawkins, William Boyd, 1838-1929
    Manchester, A.L.S. 1p. (see Sir James Paget. Collection.) Concerning a story about a cat.
  - Letter to [Sir James] Paget, April 27, 1881(?); 7x4-1/2; Huxley, Thomas Henry, 1825-1895
    A.L.S. 4p. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Is too ill to attend the dinner and lecture.
  - Letter to Sir James [Paget], Feb. 10, 1882; 5-1/4x4; Brown-Séquard, Charles Edouard, 1817-1894
    Paris, A.L.S. 3p. (see Sir James Paget. Collection...) Concerning his health. Announces his winning a prize from the Institut.